Jo Deal

(Mobile) 07595 982002 (Email) jodeal@ymail.com

PROFESSIONAL OVERVIEW:

A highly experienced in Country Risk Management Consultant, specialising in a holistic and proactive risk management solution, engaging all stakeholders with a 'can do' attitude and a clear understanding of the entire working environment. Worked closely with NGO's, DFID, USACE, and the FCO in Iraq as well as Oil and Gas Industry in Africa and the Indian Ocean gaining commercial experience as well as honing skills in multi-agency co-operation and management.

Adding business development acumen to Prince2 project management and an outstanding track record of international success, and specialising in the provision of advisory services covering security across a range of environments. A subject matter specialist, providing technical and operational guidance to ensure fulfillment of client requirements, and successfully close \$100 million contracts often whilst operating in hostile/difficult environments.

Acknowledged as a determined and persistent problem solver, dynamic self-starter, an engaging highly personable communicator, and an effective negotiator with the extensive, strategic-level, partnership building experience within international, multi-site, service oriented, matrix-managed environments.

CAREER HIGHLIGHTS INCLUDE:

DC RMS Ltd (Trading as Drum Cussac)

- Motivated a team of 200+ professionals dealing with all aspects of risk, incorporating personal risk, and maritime security within diverse and hostile environments
- Closed \$multi million (\$10m to \$100m+) contracts through provision of subject matter expertise, including risk management, security and operational planning to match client-specific requirements
 - o Oil & Gas companies include British Gas, Statoil, Ophir
 - o Shipping companies include Gaslog, TATA NYK, MOL
- Coordinated site closure and TUPE of international based staff following takeover by Ambrey Risk Ltd, concluding contracts for communications, vehicle hire and accommodation in Sri Lanka and coordinating the freighting of controlled equipment to the UK
- Project managed the off-shore security of oil & gas clients including British Gas, Statoil and Ophir, leading a 60 strong team of security professionals and 9 vessels and had responsibility/control of local budgets.
- Produced all Risk Management documents including Evacuation Plan, Medical Repatriation Plan and Journey Management Plan
- Managed the logistic support vessel in the Rea Sea, establishing and maintaining H&S protocols, implemented logistic tracking systems and providing ongoing maritime security support
- Worked in a multi-cultural environment training local nationals in Africa and Sri Lanka as well liaising with all local Government and Military contacts
- Managed transit administration In-country for security teams operating in all areas of the Indian Ocean including logistics, welfare, journey management, evacuation and medical repatriation, and liaising with international government and commercial contacts including successful negotiation of contracts

Private Security-Iraq

 Worked with the United States Army International Development representatives and the British High Commissioners in Baghdad and Basra to provide specialist security advice and support. Led a information finding local national team producing street level live intelligence to client Government agencies and NGO's, enabling successful completion of projects building schools and hospitals

CAREER HISTORY:

Jan 2014 to Jan 2015

IN-COUNTRY BASE MANAGER - Sri Lanka: DC RMS Ltd / Drum Cussac - Sub-Contractor

- Responsible for delivery of all transit operations into Sri Lanka including administration support and pastoral care of a team of 200 risk management consultants based throughout the region
- Coordinating training briefings and ensuring compliance with mandatory regulations / procedures
- · Developing emergency evacuation, medical emergency procedures and incident management plans
- Liaising with British High Commission, Local Authorities, Port Agents and International suppliers

Jan 2012 to Dec 2013

BASE MANAGER – LOGISTICS SUPPORT VESSEL – Red Sea: DC RMS Ltd - Sub-Contractor

- Appointed to oversee and manage all operations for the Logistics Support Vessel for a portfolio of blue chip clients, liaising with vessel captain and crew and supporting consultants
- Preparing daily, weekly and monthly reports and contract invoices for transition to UK office
- Providing ongoing pastoral care for field based consultants ensuring all requirements were met

Nov 2010 to Jan 2012

PROJECT MANAGER - Offshore East Africa: DC RMS Ltd / Drum Cussac - Sub-Contractor

- Responsible for managing support of off-shore oil, gas and energy blue chip client security requirements including seismic surveys and drilling projects, liaising with host nation naval teams
- Assessed client requirements and developed relationships to address onboard security issues
- Maintained close and regular liaison with local authorities, agents and client representatives
- Prepared and presented regular reports for UK head office and monitoring the deployment and recovery of teams, onboard clients and allied security vessels undertaking debrief

Aug 2009 to Nov 2010

SENIOR TEAM LEADER - Indian Ocean: DC RMS Ltd / Drum Cussac - Sub-Contractor

- Appointed to manage a Vessel Protection Team of 4 for armed and unarmed transits through the Indian Ocean and allied off-shore seismic and drilling projects through the East African region
- Undertook ship security reviews and dynamic risk assessments for Suez to Sri Lanka routes

EARLY CAREER INCLUDES:

•	Senior Team Leader	Aegis Defence Ltd	2004 - 2008
•	Personal Trainer	Deal in Fitness	1999 - 2004
•	Royal Marine Commando	Royal Marine Corps	1992 - 1999

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS:

- Leadership Management
- Business Development
- Coaching & Mentoring
- Influencing & Persuasion
- Performance Management

- Awareness Training
- Policy Enforcement
- IT / Business Communications
- Conflict Management
- Solution Provision

PROFESSIONAL TRAINING:

- Control Risks Security Management and Consultant Course- BTEC Level 4 and 5
- Maritime Firearms Competency Certificate
- Maritime Security Officer (MSO)
- Company Security Officer (CSO)
- STCW95

- IOSH Managing Safely
- Risk Management / Hostile Environments
- 3RG FPOS (I)
- Petans Offshore Safety Management
- Petans Helicopter Underwater Escape
- Hostile Environment –Close Protection

EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATIONS:

- MSc Risk, Crisis & Disaster Management to complete 2016
- Prince 2 Foundation & Practitioner to complete April 2015

Jo Deal